<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-12T22:33:32-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jasmine Mithani</title><subtitle>✨ designer, developer, researcher, &amp;&amp; data witch ✨</subtitle><entry><title type="html">📖 Cultivating a reading habit</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/25/cultivating-a-reading-habit.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="📖 Cultivating a reading habit" /><published>2020-03-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-03-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/25/cultivating-a-reading-habit</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/25/cultivating-a-reading-habit.html">&lt;p&gt;I read all the time as a child. On long car rides my parents chided me for having my head buried in a book, cajoling me to look outside at the scenery. Like many people, I broke my reading stride when I started college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six years ago I learned about the 52 Book Challenge, where you try to read a book a week for a year. I was taking a year off from school, and was bored and alone in my parents house in the foothills. One year of college had broken me physically and emotionally. I was focusing on building my health back up and figuring out what I wanted to do with my life. I reached out for a community online and discovered the book challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During that first year away at university, I stopped all extracurricular reading. Stress, sleep deprivation, and the trials of late teendom left me with little energy or desire to read books. It was difficult to gaze at more words after forcing my way through pages of academic text; I generally wanted to stare at a wall when I was done. But then I was at home in LA, unable to drive, alone except for my parents and two friends. I had lots of free time between the few credits I was taking at the local community college and my temporary unemployment. I began to read again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing this now, in 2020, I didn’t think it would take so long to return to a regular habit of reading average-length books. At first I was striving for a return to old reading habits, but over time my goal has shifted. I still push myself to read, but I don’t pressure myself to read the same way I did when I was younger (my memories of which have a dusting of nostalgia). “How I used to read” is a false idea: I was a kid, my parents monitored what I read, I didn’t care how many books I was reading, my time spent online was extremely different. So the modern goal was reading fifty-two books, and now it’s evolved into a desire to read widely, balancing comfort zones and pushing limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I hear people lament that they don’t read anymore, I tend to recount my journey to my current reading habit. I didn’t begin to keep track of my number of books read more formally until 2017, but I have odd scraps noting which books I read in 2014-2016. From this, I’ve developed a sort of a schedule, if you will. The main driver is increasing the number of books you read, advancing to the point where you can comfortably read several-hundred-page fictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few comments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I didn’t include young adult or middle grade fiction because I’m not drawn to them. That can be an excellent way to start reading more—perhaps even re-reading books you enjoyed when you were younger, then working up to more recent works.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I decided years ago that if I didn’t like a book, I wouldn’t force myself to finish it. Sticking with a book I didn’t like often made me resent reading, and I felt I wasted my time. Reading is enjoyable to me, not a chore, and allowing myself to put down a book that didn’t capture my interest was freeing. That doesn’t mean I give up on hard books, just that if something is awful I know I can (metaphorically) chuck it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’ve more recently become more aware of the representation in books I read: gender, sexuality, race, disability. I’m mindful of the books I read now, and am intentional about prioritizing authors of color. While I hope everyone is aware of their reading patterns, it can be overwhelming. My advice is to pay attention to what you’re reading, but don’t feel guilty. Make a note of it and set a goal for the next year (or next reading sprint).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I found the structure of a challenge motivating, as I’m unfortunately competitive. Even when I didn’t complete the 52 Book Challenge for several years, it gave me something to strive for. Look at challenges as a way to motivate yourself—there are plenty ranging from reading authors of color to more gamified book bingo—but if they feel constricting, don’t pressure yourself to commit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m a data nerd so I like keeping track of metadata about all the books I read. I use Goodreads, and this year started using my own spreadsheet to monitor custom metrics based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://smartbitchestrashybooks.com/2020/01/track-your-2020-reading-with-this-nifty-spreadsheet/&quot;&gt;this template&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://smartbitchestrashybooks.com/&quot;&gt;Smart Bitches, Trashy Books&lt;/a&gt;. Whichever method you choose, I urge you to keep a list of all the books you read. (Feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;https://goodreads.com/quantboireads&quot;&gt;add me&lt;/a&gt; on Goodreads!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without further ado, here are the steps I took to build up my reading again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Read lots of very short books. Poetry is my recommendation, because there are so few words on the page. Novellas work too. Anything that will build your confidence about reading books and finishing them. Recommendations: &lt;em&gt;Urban Tumbleweed&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Spring and All&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Binti&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;I Don’t Think Of You (Until I Do)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Shopgirl&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Graphite&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Salad Anniversary&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Read short story collections and/or anthologies. There’s a lot of variety, and finishing each story or section gives a sense of accomplishment. If you don’t like a story, you can skip it or power through knowing it’ll be over in a few pages. Recommendations: &lt;em&gt;The Girl’s Guide To Hunting And Fishing&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Self Help&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want to read more fiction, start reading long graphic novels. &lt;em&gt;The Sculptor&lt;/em&gt; by Scott McCleod built up my confidence to follow a single plot line for a sustained period, and also finish a huge book. Recommendations: &lt;em&gt;The Heart Of Thomas&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Sculptor&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;What Is Obscenity?&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bitch Planet&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To get comfortable reading longer books, move to genre fiction. I absolutely love romance novels; I can binge them and finish them in a day or two. Many are 300-400 pages. With genre fiction, there is an agreement between the author and the reader to stick to conventions. The plot structure can be predictable, like in romance, or maybe it’s the fast pace, such as thrillers. Conventional genre fiction almost always has a conclusion: the main characters have a happily ever after, the mystery is solved. Especially in these turbulent times, formulas are comforting. Recommendations: &lt;em&gt;Look For Her&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Do You Want To Start A Scandal&lt;/em&gt;, The Crossfire Series.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Read “light” nonfiction: business books, self-help, pop science or anthropology. Recommendations: &lt;em&gt;Seven Days In The Art World&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Choose Wonder Over Worry&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;My Morning Routine&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bad With Money&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Read whatever you want! This isn’t the end, though. Watch for patterns in your reading, and start challenging yourself with books out of your comfort zone. (This doesn’t mean tackling meaty philosophy or the like, for me that guidance included a YA fantasy book.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m so sad when people tell me they wish they could develop their reading habit, because reading has been crucial to my understanding of the world and provided solace through the strains of everyday life. If you want to talk about your reading journey, have questions, or want book recommendations &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jazzmyth&quot;&gt;hit me up on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. ✨&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Walking through how I taught myself to love reading again.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">🏆 2019 Success List</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/28/2019-success-list.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🏆 2019 Success List" /><published>2020-01-28T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-01-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/01/28/2019-success-list</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/01/28/2019-success-list.html">&lt;p&gt;Writing a 2019 success list was hard. Is hard. Writing this intro, I haven’t even started listing accomplishments. Which is silly, because there are a few milestones I can easily spit out (like a new job).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developed a website and &lt;a href=&quot;https://riskandreach.erikson.edu/illinois-map/&quot;&gt;interactive map&lt;/a&gt; for the Erikson Institute&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spent quality time working through tricky data with SQL&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spoke on a panel about careers in tech at a community college, was thanked afterward for talking about mental health&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gave a talk at a local meetup about Leaflet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gave my first 45-minute talk at PearConf—which was also the first time I’d been paid as a speaker&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Impromptu participation on a panel on careers in data visualization at visfestunconf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developed a huge new feature for LA Metro’s instance of Councilmatic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ignored a lot of advice and quit a job without anything planned&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;got a new job at an exciting workplace&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helped hire an EIC and managing editor at the weekly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;joined the SSW board at staff representative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;began working with an ADHD coach&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sought treatment for my sleep issues, eventually diagnosed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;titrated off of a medication i had been on for six years and am doing much better&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;took in a foster cat!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;moved to an apartment where i’m a lot happier. environment is important.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transitioned to full-time remote work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;worked under the lead of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/juruwolfe&quot;&gt;Julia Wolfe&lt;/a&gt; to add in FiveThirtyEight’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/polls/president-primary-d/national/&quot;&gt;polling averages&lt;/a&gt; in chart form&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;open-sourced a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/datamade/how-to/blob/master/ux/project-research-and-interviews.md&quot;&gt;guide to user research&lt;/a&gt; I wrote with &lt;a href=&quot;https://derekeder.com/&quot;&gt;Derek Eder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;whizzed by my goal of reading 70 books and read 100 instead!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set three concrete, measurable professional goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard because two of my three professional goals are aligned with my personal ambitions, and but I hadn’t done the work to vocalize and define them. For instance, I enjoy public speaking and it’s a skill I want to strengthen. However, I stopped seeking out those opportunities because I felt it was more important to focus on my day-to-day job duties. And that was the right prioritization, but I didn’t replace it the joy I got from public speaking with anything. This year, I’m taking stock of my energy and which activities breed satisfaction so I can invest in my own happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an election year at FiveThirtyEight, and the Olympics kick off in the summer. I’m excited thinking about what this list will look like next year. ✨&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Last year's accomplishments that I remember.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">👓 Reflecting on 2019</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/28/2019-reflection.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="👓 Reflecting on 2019" /><published>2019-12-28T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-12-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/12/28/2019-reflection</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/28/2019-reflection.html">&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to start this reflection is by reviewing &lt;a href=&quot;https://jmithani.com/2019/01/15/2018-success-list.html&quot;&gt;the intentions for the year&lt;/a&gt; I laid out in January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;read-70-books-including-a-conscious-to-be-read-pile&quot;&gt;Read 70 books including a conscious “to be read” pile.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my first full year legitimately free from education, I hit my seventy book goal in September. After that, I didn’t read for a few weeks, which utterly shocked me. Rather I was reading, but not finishing, books. Having a reading goal is a toss-up; on one hand it’s pushing myself to keep reading and be conscious of what I read, and on the other it can favor finishing books over savoring longer or more difficult reads. It is a challenge, but is it the right kind of challenge? I have my doubts, but I like doing it. I increased my goal to one hundred books and immediately began reading at my usual pace. Weird. As of this writing I’m at ninety-seven, I have a whole stack of books and one cross-country flight planned, so one hundred is inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020: Add more structure to the reading challenge, specifying types of books.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;continue-to-listen&quot;&gt;Continue to listen.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I have to share something I’m good at, I always say listening. It’s part of what makes me an excellent user researcher. I can listen to someone talk about their issues, distill that information, and provide meaningful recommendations. Or not! I read an article about listening ages ago that has stuck with me. In it, the author shared an anecdote about a friend whose family member passed away. The author, in an effort to relate to their friend, talked about how their father passed away at a young age and how they dealt with it. Their friend become angry, accusing them of winning the “depression olympics.” The point of the story is that so often we try to relate to others through our own experiences, but when someone is sharing they don’t want to hear about you. They might not want a solution. They just want to talk, and be heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This intention was a bit of a doozy, as I wasn’t going to suddenly unlearn everything I know about meaningful communication. I was committing to maintaining this practice in times when that would be challenged. I think I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020: How can this be challenged? How can I maintain a commitment to listening in the face of these challenges?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learn-more-about-prison-abolition-and-seek-opportunities-to-ethically-support-the-struggle&quot;&gt;Learn more about prison abolition and seek opportunities to ethically support the struggle.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned some more about abolitionism, but mostly through following people like Mariame Kaba on Twitter, which isn’t the type of dedication I envisioned when writing this intention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that held me back from learning more about the subject was uncertainty over “how to ethically support the struggle.” In the latter half of 2019 I started applying for jobs, and several of them were in newsrooms. (Well, actually just one…FiveThirtyEight. But I planned to apply to more.) I have a lot of anxiety about conflicts of interest, and I let that fear be an excuse for not learning about difficult subjects that I didn’t know how to support in my current circumstances. I’ve thought about pitching stories about incarceration in the US, but haven’t laid out concrete steps to make that happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020: How can this topic be explored in a data-driven, educational manner?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;refocus-who-and-what-i-want-to-advocate-for-and-which-resources-i-will-invest-in-that&quot;&gt;Refocus who and what I want to advocate for, and which resources I will invest in that.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is somewhat related to the above. I’m highly empathetic, and can become overwhelmed when learning about injustices; I can despair over how I can(not) help. My prior chief method of fiscally supporting organizations deeply engaged with combating certain issues is no longer something I’m comfortable with. I’ve had to assess the tools in my possession—which are myriad and powerful when I can harness them—and determine how best I can personally combat injustices. As a journalist this means sharing stories that are overlooked, finding answers to difficult questions, and explaining complex processes in an accessible manner. As a developer, journalist, writer, democratizing information is my discipline. And I’m good at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020: Accept that terrible things are happening everywhere, and I can’t fix all of them. I do have some power, and I need to learn how to wield that in an ethical way.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;continue-to-prioritize-my-loved-ones-but-not-over-myself&quot;&gt;Continue to prioritize my loved ones, but not over myself.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This declaration was so vague. It had the energy of something you’d see in script on an Instagram post, but the follow-through was less clear. Now I have to ask myself, what does prioritization look like? What does choosing myself over someone I love look like? What boundaries am I going to put in place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020: What do these boundaries look like? How do they continue to evolve?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These thoughts are going to percolate while I think about my 2019 success list and goals for 2020. While writing, I had to hold myself back from analyzing what I’m going to do differently. I want to take time to read this over and come back to it before I jump into ways I can set more effective intentions. Update coming soon. ✨&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Revisiting my intentions for the year.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">🏡 Unlearning shame via remote work</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/01/unlearning-shame-remote-work.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🏡 Unlearning shame via remote work" /><published>2019-12-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-12-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/12/01/unlearning-shame-remote-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/01/unlearning-shame-remote-work.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve finished my fourth week of full-time remote work as a visual journalist at FiveThirtyEight, and I feel latent forms of stress continuing to uncoil within me. Though it’s only been a month I can overwhelmingly say being remote—or elements of remote life—has tremendously helped me become a better developer and healthier human being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first time being remote for a full eight-hour day, every day. I didn’t realize the amount of mental navigation working in a traditional office atmosphere required for me. I no longer start my day off with the stress of a commute and having to constantly be aware of the time, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.additudemag.com/is-your-spouse-always-late-running-on-adhd-time/&quot;&gt;documented difficulty associated with ADHD&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m understanding now that a major source of anxiety is how I appear to others. I’m no longer worried about looking presentable to anyone but myself. I get dressed in comfortable clothes and don’t wear makeup. (A plus for my skin.) Physical presentation is just a piece of this. Now that I don’t see anyone save thrice-weekly video calls, I can distill that I carried a lot of shame over how I worked best into the office with me. This compounds on the shame of having disabilities, and of being chronically ill. Visible disability accommodations are essential to my ability to be productive, but reinforce how different I am from other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a circadian rhythm disorder, and sometimes my internal clock gets off the regular “normal sleeping hours” track. I also suffer from insomnia. In past jobs I’ve struggled with working around these obstacles; even if I woke up an hour late I would still have to get out of bed, shower, get dressed, eat (or else I’ll get nauseous while commuting), commute to work, and then start my day. Plus there’s the shame aspect, of not performing the same way or being as “productive” as my coworkers. After several days of shitty sleep, I’m basically a zombie. In an open office I can’t take a nap for twenty minutes to deal with that fatigue. I can’t get up and walk around every half hour to burn off nervous energy. Without the restrictions of acceptable behavior in an office, and the self-censoring that came with it, I’m figuring out the best way I work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, no one cares if I stare at the ceiling while trying to debug something in my head, because no one can see me. The furthest I have to go to commute is the four feet to my desk. And that’s freeing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, remote life isn’t all sunshine and roses. I’m mostly saying that as a caveat, because I’m sure more concerns will arise in the future. Right now it’s freaking awesome. I do need to be more intentional about socializing and am trying to make a schedule. I did not sign up for the working space like I planned to because not having to leave my house during Chicago winters is a definite perk. I’m hoping to sign up in the summer, so I can bike there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reflection has also prompted me to remember to trust myself. I had been thinking about working remotely full-time for a while; I’d done plenty of remote work before, but it was always outside the confines of nine to five. I talked to many people I knew about their experiences, did lots of research online, and tried to make balanced pro-and-con lists. I was worried that my excitement was leading me to ignore difficulties of remote work I hadn’t considered or wasn’t taking seriously. The reality is that remote work has not only raised my quality of life in the ways I expected, but it has exceeded them. I can cook myself multiple meals a day, eat healthy snacks on schedule, do my full skincare routine, cuddle my cats…I can list so many improvements to my daily existence. And I never expected I’d end up working to understand myself better, learning how I work best and in what kinds of environments my disabled body and mind can thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to this future. ✨&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Though it's only been a month I can overwhelmingly say being remote—or elements of remote life—has tremendously helped me become a better developer and healthier human being.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">💼 Advice on data visualization career paths</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/09/09/data-viz-career-advice.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="💼 Advice on data visualization career paths" /><published>2019-09-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-09-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/09/09/data-viz-career-advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/09/09/data-viz-career-advice.html">&lt;p&gt;I had the privilege to participate in a panel of career paths in data visualization alongside heavyweights &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.williamrchase.com/&quot;&gt;Will Chase (UPenn)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://sxywu.com/&quot;&gt;Shirley Wu (freelance)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://martingonzalez.net/&quot;&gt;Martín González (The Economist)&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/blakeirvine/&quot;&gt;Blake Irvine (Netflix)&lt;/a&gt;. Many people seemed to find my answers useful, so I’ve documented them here with a bit of hindsight editing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-your-current-plan-for-professional-development&quot;&gt;What is your current plan for professional development?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confession: I had a better answer than the one I shared in person. I had it in my head but when I got the mic it was swept out of my mind. I’m adding that answer too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to invest in systems. At the Weekly, our analyses and visualizations are one-offs. We don’t have a standard toolkit, onboarding for graphics, or style guide. I have ideas for some of these, but the overarching question is how to create an efficient technical system that allows space for people to learn and grow. I would love if we used our own version of the dailygraphics rig, but if someone joins the paper with only experience in R it can be too much to grasp. So in short, I am thinking about how to create a powerful, standardized visualization system in which onboarding people with a variety of technical backgrounds is easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-can-you-share-about-job-titles-which-to-go-for-what-they-mean&quot;&gt;What can you share about job titles? (Which to go for, what they mean…)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m currently a developer at DataMade, where we have three roles: developer, lead developer, and partner. Having a generic job title has allowed me fluidity in how I represent my work. In regard to job titles, I worry about three things: that it accurately conveys the work I do, that I’m not being pidgeon-holed into front-end development because I use D3, and that the title sufficiently indicates my technical authority. The example of Netflix using Senior Data Visualization Engineer is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In journalism, this is a much more controversial topic. In data visualization in general, jobs titles are scattered and there isn’t a solid job definition that would provide terminological guidance on the role. If you work in journalism, whether or not you are called a journalist can weigh whether or not you are given credit for a piece. Many data journalists contribute to articles and don’t receive a byline, or graphics aren’t attributed to a specific individual. In this case, arguing for “journalist” in the job title can be crucial. If you aren’t contributing to written stories, there is an array of names including News Apps Developer, and Graphics Editor (which still implies a level of journalistic skill).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are switching industries between news and something else, title can play a role. (Get it? I’m hilarious.) I’ve never worked in hiring, but as an applicant I emphasize different parts of my past work depending on the job I’m doing. If I have flexibility in job title I can use, all the better e.g. Graphics Reporter versus Visualization Specialist versus Data Journalist versus Developer, assuming all are accurate. Ideally whoever is looking at your resume cares more about your work and skills than titles or degrees. Usually if I see a company insisting on a computer science degree, it’s a personal red flag for culture fit&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-do-you-motivate-yourself-to-keep-learning&quot;&gt;How do you motivate yourself to keep learning?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work toward some higher purpose. South Side Weekly seeks to cover stories that are overlooked or misrepresented by other media outlets. It’s community-driven mission resonates with my values, and that drives me to do my best. Sometimes it adds unproductive pressure, but for the most part it motivates me to know that my work is giving back to the community I care about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-advice-would-you-give-to-someone-just-graduating-and-moving-into-their-career&quot;&gt;What advice would you give to someone just graduating and moving into their career?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Network.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find a job you like? Find someone with the same job at the company and email/LinkedIn/Tweet asking to learn more about the company and role. I try to reach out to people whose lived experience is similar to mine, which usually means queer or people of color. Don’t be smarmy. I genuinely want to learn about different people and their backgrounds, and how they got to where they are. I want to know about what the culture is like for people like me at this company. Be thoughtful and respectful of someone’s time. Include a few direct questions to answer in a twenty minute call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See someplace you’d like to work someday? Message someone and ask for advice. All the same advice from above applies. I go back and cringe at the emails I sent to partners at design firms I was interested in talking to. But you know what? They replied and I met them in their offices. If you write an honest and respectful email (no dreaded “can I pick your brain…”), there is no reason to stall on sending it. If it’s ignored, that’s okay. It’s not a rejection. Email is hard. Don’t give up—there’s always someone else you can learn from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Environment.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about how you want to structure your life. What kind of work do you want to do? Would you be happy working in D3 everyday if you would only be making dashboards? Could you join a place as a developer, and evangelize the team to data visualization after working there six months? Or could you be happy working a job unrelated to visualization, but allowed you the creative space to work on side projects on nights and weekends?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Meetups.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, this is really an extension of #1. But reaching out 1:1 can be difficult, and sometimes going to an organized networking event can be easier to navigate. I’ve found ones with some structure most helpful when I’m in a new city. For example, Code for DC has a mandatory onboarding session for all new folx before they can jump in and work on a project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an outline of what I tell people (or wish I had the time to tell people!) when they ask me for career advice. It was a novelty to be on a career paths panel because of how junior I felt compared to the other participants. However, I’ve certainly done many different types of work in many types of environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My final piece of advice is something I’m still working on, which is not to sell yourself short. I fret about my age and experience and about being a minority, all things that seem to discredit me as I try to build up my expertise. But hell I’ve done a lot in a short period of time, and I’ve had to crash through hurdles others haven’t even thought of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data visualization is a new field, and most of the career advice can be summed up as hone in on what work you want to do, what concessions you can make in order to do that work, and then blaze forward. Visualization encompasses so many industries and technologies—reach out to the community (you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jazzmyth&quot;&gt;Tweet me&lt;/a&gt; at any time) if you need guidance. Ignore naysayers. You’re going to do something great. ✨&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Data visualization is a new field, and most of the career advice can be summed up as hone in on what work you want to do, what concessions you can make in order to do that work, and then blaze forward.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">⚖️ Personal rules of engagement</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/24/standards.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="⚖️ Personal rules of engagement" /><published>2019-01-24T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-01-24T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/24/standards</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/24/standards.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been creating standards for myself, most intentionally over the past year but unconsciously throughout my life. I’ve debated stating them publicly, as I worry that they might come off as accusatory or bragging to others, especially because I’m not seeking praise for setting these. What made me change my mind about sharing them is the realization that if I don’t, then I can’t be held accountable—and is that the kind of commitment I want to be making?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following are particularly important to me as someone who works in technology, journalism, and the non-profit sphere. Marginalized people in journalism and technology regularly experience discrimination and harassment. Non-profits can use their status to underpay and de-value the work their employees put into the organization. Creating these rules for engagement in professional communities is one of the ways I am trying to combat this abuse. I’m not particularly popular, or well-known, but deciding these and keeping to them at the beginning of my career will guide any influence I accrue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the rules I’ve set for myself for navigating the professional world. To be updated, constantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I do not advertise or endorse internships or fellowships which pay below a living wage; at minimum $15/hour, more for cities such as New York or Washington, DC. Likewise for jobs that only offer school credit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will not attend any conference that does not have a code of conduct. A good code of conduct should adequately provide resources for those who experience harassment, and define harassment; discrimination based upon gender identity, race or ethnicity, religion, appearance, or disability should be explicitly banned. If there is an event I want to attend that does not have a code of conduct, I will write to the organizers and request one, along with links to examples.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I will not speak at venues that do not have gender-neutral restrooms. I will make this a requirement for when I speak, and bring it up to the organizer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I speak at an event, I will ask if a government ID is required to enter the venue. If so, I will ask for accommodations for those who do not possess that or who have an ID that is no longer accurate. ✨&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Standards I hold myself to, professionally.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">🏆 2018 Success List</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/15/2018-success-list.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="🏆 2018 Success List" /><published>2019-01-15T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-01-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/15/2018-success-list</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/15/2018-success-list.html">&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mindfulproductivityblog.com/podcasts-by-episode/50&quot;&gt;this episode&lt;/a&gt; of The Mindful Productivity Podcast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2018&quot;&gt;2018&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consistently telling people other than my cat and parents that i love them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;graduated college&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.npr.org/dailygraphics/graphics/cardi-b-over-time-20180404/img/cardi-bodak.png&quot;&gt;kicked&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2018/02/23/586236738/coal-jobs-have-gone-up-under-trump-but-not-because-of-his-policies&quot;&gt;ass&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2018/01/22/578930256/undocumented-irish-unexpectedly-caught-in-trumps-immigration-dragnet&quot;&gt;interning&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2018/03/16/594253182/kentucky-votes-to-ban-child-marriage&quot;&gt;at&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/ed/2018/02/15/581895659/whos-missing-from-america-s-colleges-rural-high-school-graduates&quot;&gt;NPR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;started work as a developer at &lt;a href=&quot;https://datamade.us&quot;&gt;datamade&lt;/a&gt; and haven’t apologized for my technical background&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;owned up to my background in tech and actively reference &lt;a href=&quot;https://linkedin.com/in/jmithani&quot;&gt;my prior work experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;requested &lt;a href=&quot;https://datamade.us/documents/DataMade%20Anti-Harassment%20Policy%20and%20Procedures-v1.2.pdf&quot;&gt;an anti-harassment policy&lt;/a&gt; be drafted on my first day at datamade (it was, thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://beamalsky.fyi/&quot;&gt;Bea Malsky&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;designed and kicked off &lt;a href=&quot;https://datamade.us/blog/mentorship-program/&quot;&gt;datamade mentorship program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;submit to two conference CFP’s&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;spoke at &lt;a href=&quot;https://srccon.org/sessions/#proposal-disability-in-newsroom&quot;&gt;three&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://sched.co/GY8g&quot;&gt;conferences&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://guidebook.com/guide/147793/event/21682714/&quot;&gt;one international&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;talked about having disabilities publicly for the first time (as part of an aforementioned talk)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;visited two new states (Minnesota and Tennessee)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;travelled outside of the continental US for the first time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sought targeted treatment for my sleep problems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;read 61 books&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://southsideweekly.com/unerasable-patricia-frazier-poetry/&quot;&gt;actually&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://southsideweekly.com/for-she-wrote-kwyn-riley/&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://southsideweekly.com/best-south-side-south-loop-2018/&quot;&gt;a few&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://southsideweekly.com/best-south-side-south-loop-2018/#best-sugar-rush&quot;&gt;pieces&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://southsideweekly.com/best-south-side-chinatown-2018/#best-boba-trends&quot;&gt;for&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://southsideweekly.com/&quot;&gt;the weekly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;began editing pieces for the weekly regardless of genre&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;began to put down strong boundaries on my time and abilities to take on new commitments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prioritized my health and happiness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;journaled weekly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2019&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;70 books including a conscious “to be read” pile&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;continue to listen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;learn more about prison abolition and seek opportunities to ethically support the struggle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;refocus who and what i want to advocate for, and which resources i will invest in that&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;continue to prioritize my loved ones, but not over myself ✨&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Last year in brief, a few weeks late.</summary></entry></feed>